Finding Aid for the Jean Renoir Papers PASC.0105
UCLA Library Special Collections
- Part II - Correspondence
  - OCTOBER 1951
    - J.R. and Dido Renoir in Italy for LE CARROSSE D'OR - J.R. undergoes operation on his leg - includes photocopied correspondence. Includes correspondence regarding or with: * Odets, Clifford * Guillaume, Louis * Dewalde, Jean * Coryell, Robert * RIVER, THE * CARROSSE D'OR, LE (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - NOVEMBER 1951
    - Arrangements for LE CARROSSE D'OR - includes photocopied correspondence. Includes correspondence regarding or with: * Alliata, Francesco * CARROSSE D'OR, LE * Odets, Clifford (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - DECEMBER 1951
    - News of friends - J.R.'s percentage of receipts for release of UNE PARTIE DE CAMPAGNE - includes photocopied correspondence. Includes correspondence regarding or with: * Dewalde, Jean * Guillaume, Louis * Odets, Clifford * Sen Gupta, Ram (Box 11, Folder 12)
    - Death of Robert Flaherty - Pierre Renoir performing in N.Y.C. - news of family and friends. Includes correspondence regarding or with: * Flaherty, Frances * Renoir, Pierre * Renoir, Alain * Richter, Hans * Slade, Gabrielle * Lewin, Albert * Nichols, Dudley * Mason, Pamela * Flaherty, Robert (Box 15, Folder 19)
  - JANUARY 1952
    - News of family and friends - birth of J.R.'s grandson - J.R.'s refusal to dub LE CARROSSE D'OR. Includes correspondence regarding or with: * Nichols, Dudley * Radha * Renoir, Claude, Jr. * Alliata, Francesco * Renoir, John (Box 11, Folder 13)
  - FEBRUARY 1952
    - Shooting LE CARROSSE D'OR. Includes correspondence regarding or with: * Godden, Rumer * Alliata, Francesco * CARROSSE D'OR, LE (Box 11, Folder 14)
  - MARCH 1952
    - Shooting of LE CARROSSE D'OR - television contract for THE SOUTHERNER - inquiry into J.R.'s percentage of receipts for re-release of UNE PARTIE DE CAMPAGNE. Includes correspondence regarding or with: * Dewalde, Jean * Alliata, Francesco * CARROSSE D'OR, LE * Braunberger, Pierre * PARTIE DE CAMPAGNE, UNE * Guillaume, Louis * SOUTHERNER, THE (Box 11, Folder 15)
  - APRIL 1952
    - Work on LE CARROSSE D'OR - American censorship cuts of the film - problems with the crew not being paid. Includes correspondence regarding or with: * Alliata, Francesco * Renoir, Claude, Jr. * CARROSSE D'OR, LE * Harrison, Kay * Dewalde, Jean * Braunberger, Pierre * PARTIE DE CAMPAGNE, UNE (Box 11, Folder 16)
  - MAY 1952
    - Work on LE CARROSSE D'OR. Includes correspondence regarding or with: * Odets, Clifford (Box 11, Folder 17)
  - JUNE 1952
    - News of friends - death of John Garfield - working on LE CARROSSE D'OR - includes photocopied correspondence. Includes correspondence regarding or with: * Avronsart, Armand * Guillaume, Louis * Alliata, Francesco * CARROSSE D'OR, LE * Nichols, Dudley * Odets, Clifford * Garfield, John (Box 11, Folder 18)
  - JULY 1952
    - Work on technicolor prints of LE CARROSSE D'OR - project of a book on Pierre-Auguste Renoir. Includes correspondence regarding or with: * Lauer, Jean * Masse, Jacques * Benouville, Pierre de * Alliata, Francesco * CARROSSE D'OR, LE * Dewalde, Jean (Box 11, Folder 19)
  - AUGUST 1952
    - Projects - news of friends - J.R. trying to acquire rights to LA GRANDE ILLUSION for re-release. Includes correspondence regarding or with: * Guillaume, Louis * Geddes, Virgil * GRANDE ILLUSION, LA (Box 11, Folder 20)
  - SEPTEMBER 1952
    - Delays in printing copies of LE CARROSSE D'OR. Includes correspondence regarding or with: * Alliata, Francesco * CARROSSE D'OR, LE (Box 11, Folder 21)
  - OCTOBER 1952
    - LE CARROSSE D'OR: American censorship problems, working on titles - includes photocopied correspondence. Includes correspondence regarding or with: * Salemson, Harold * Breen, Joseph * Hawkins, David * CARROSSE D'OR, LE * Dewalde, Jean * Renoir, Claude, Jr. * Smith, Bessie * Alliata, Francesco * Odets, Clifford (Box 11, Folder 22)
  - NOVEMBER 1952
    - LE CARROSSE D'OR: American censorship problems - invitation for J.R. to speak at Ohio University - news of family. Includes correspondence regarding or with: * Renoir, Claude, Jr. * Renoir, Alain * Salemson, Harold * CARROSSE D'OR, LE * Alliata, Francesco * Breen, Joseph (Box 11, Folder 23)
  - DECEMBER 1952
    - News of friends - J.R. speaks at Ohio University - Christmas greetings - release of and publicity for LE CARROSSE D'OR. Includes correspondence regarding or with: * Guillaume, Louis * CARROSSE D'OR, LE * Judd, Forrest * Magnani, Anna * Macchi, Guilio * Evans, Ernestine * Seigfried, Earl * Bergman, Ingrid * Rossellini, Roberto * Renoir, Claude, Jr. (Box 11, Folder 24)
    - Receipts for LE CARROSSE D'OR - death of Pierre Renoir. Includes correspondence regarding or with: * CARROSSE D'OR, LE * Guillaume, Louis * Slade, Gabrielle * Renoir, Pierre (Box 15, Folder 20)
  - JANUARY 1953
    - News of friends - release of LE CARROSSE D'OR - re-release of LA REGLE DU JEU - request for article for Les Cahiers du Cinema. Includes correspondence regarding or with: * Sen Gupta, Ram * CARROSSE D'OR, LE * REGLE DU JEU, LA * Salemson, Harold * Dewalde, Jean * Grierson, John * Tessier, Valentine * Nijinsky, Romola * Doniol-Valcroze, Jacques * Alliata, Francesco (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - FEBRUARY 1953
    - News of family and friends - reactions to LE CARROSSE D'OR - re-release of LA REGLE DU JEU - project "The Poachers" - project book on Pierre-Auguste Renoir - includes photocopied correspondence. Includes correspondence regarding or with: * Walters, Patricia * Renoir, Claude, Sr. * CARROSSE D'OR, LE * Doynel, Ginette * Guillaume, Louis * Salemson, Harold * Kresel, Lee * REGLE DU JEU, LA * Odets, Clifford * POACHERS, THE (project) (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - MARCH 1953
    - LE CARROSSE D'OR: contracts and reactions to the film - re-release of LA REGLE DU JEU - J.R.'s rights to his old films - news of family and friends - state of the Hollywood film industry. Includes correspondence regarding or with: * Chaplin, Charlie * Guillaume, Louis * Doynel, Ginette * Sen Gupta, Ram * CARROSSE D'OR, LE * REGLE DU JEU, LA * Dewalde, Jean * RIVER, THE * Salemson, Harold * O'Neill, Charles * Renoir, Claude, Jr. * Singji, Prince Fateh * Lamont, Duncan * Loew, Marcus * SOUTHERNER, THE (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - APRIL 1953
    - News of friends - release of LE CARROSSE D'OR - problems with the financial dealing of THE RIVER. Includes correspondence regarding or with: * O'Neill, Charles * Sen Gupta, Ram * Godden, Rumer * Guillaume, Louis * Singji, Prince Fateh * RIVER, THE * CARROSSE D'OR, LE * Alliata, Francesco * Magnani, Anna (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - MAY 1953
    - Distribution problems with LE CARROSSE D'OR in U.S.A. - J.R. workingon a book on Pierre-Auguste Renoir - news of friends - includes photocopied correspondence. Includes correspondence regarding or with: * Odets, Clifford * Nichols, Dudley * CARROSSE D'OR, LE * Renoir, Claude, Sr. * Kresel, Lee * Radha * Godden, Rumer * Cerf, Bennett (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - JUNE 1953
    - Problems with U.S.A. distribution of LE CARROSSE D'OR - news of friends - project: stage direction of "Six Characters In Search Of An Author". Includes correspondence regarding or with: * Renoir, Claude, Jr. * Doynel, Ginette * Guillaume, Louis * Pascal, Gabriel * Salemson, Harold * SIX CHARACTERS IN SEARCH .. (project) (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - JULY 1953
    - News of friends - problems with the reimbursement of investment capital for THE RIVER - project "Six Characters In Search Of An Author" with Gabriel Pascal - U.S.A. distribution problems of LE CARROSSE D'OR - J.R. working on a book about Pierre-Auguste Renoir - includes photocopied correspondence. Includes correspondence regarding or with: * Salemson, Harold * CARROSSE D'OR, LE * Guillaume, Louis * Singji, Prince Fateh * RIVER, THE * Pascal, Gabriel * Cerf, Bennett * Koch, Carl * Radha * Sen Gupta, Ram * Baudot, Jeanne * Odets, Clifford * SIX CHARACTERS IN SEARCH .. (project) (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - AUGUST 1953
    - News of friends - problems with U.S.A. distribution of LE CARROSSE D'OR - invitations - project "The Lady From The Sea" - includes photocopied correspondence. Includes correspondence regarding or with: * Odets, Clifford * Godden, Rumer * Salemson, Harold * Seaton, George * Macchi, Guilio * Guillaume, Louis * Durant, Tim * Bergman, Ingrid * Renoir, Alain * Renoir, Claude, Jr. * CARROSSE D'OR, LE * LADY FROM THE SEA (project) (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - SEPTEMBER 1953
    - U.S.A. premiere of LE CARROSSE D'OR delayed - project "Van Gogh". Includes correspondence regarding or with: * CARROSSE D'OR, LE * Dewalde, Jean * Guillaume, Louis * Baudot, Jeanne * Rosenfield, Jonas, Jr. * VINCENT VAN GOGH (project) (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - OCTOBER 1953
    - Reactions to LE CARROSSE D'OR - project "Vincent Van Gogh". Includes correspondence regarding or with: * Dewalde, Jean * VINCENT VAN GOGH (project) * Guillaume, Louis * Stern, Stewart * Coryell, Robert * CARROSSE D'OR, LE (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - NOVEMBER 1953
    - Problems with financial dealings of THE RIVER - project "Van Gogh" with Van Heflin - news of friends. Includes correspondence regarding or with: * Coryell, Robert * Singji, Prince Fateh * Heflin, Van * Vaughan, Olwen * Lewin, Albert * Nichols, Dudley * Simenon, Denise * VINCENT VAN GOGH (project) (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - DECEMBER 1953
    - Project "Van Gogh" with Van Heflin - news of friends. Includes correspondence regarding or with: * Guillaume, Louis * Lewin, Albert * Loew, David * Nichols, Dudley * VINCENT VAN GOGH (project) (Box 12, Folder 12)
    - News of family and friends. Includes correspondence regarding or with: * Renoir, Alain * Delorme, Danielle * Slade, Gabrielle * Caron, Leslie (Box 15, Folder 21)
  - JANUARY 1954
    - J.R. named in a publication by the California Legislative Committee on Un-American Activities - reactions to LE CARROSSE D'OR - news of friends. Includes correspondence regarding or with: * Lewin, Albert * CARROSSE D'OR, LE * Nichols, Dudley * Renoir, Claude, Sr. (Box 12, Folder 13)
  - FEBRUARY 1954
    - Project "Van Gogh" with Van Heflin - news of the House Un-American Activities hearings - request by the Cinematheque Francaise for a copy of LA GRANDE ILLUSION. Includes correspondence regarding or with: * Nichols, Dudley * Langlois, Henri * Heflin, Van * VINCENT VAN GOGH (project) (Box 12, Folder 14)
  - MARCH 1954
    - Project "Van Gogh" with Van Heflin - death of Bette Odets - news of friends - includes photocopied correspondence. Includes correspondence regarding or with: * Renoir, Claude, Sr. * Guillaume, Louis * Odets, Clifford * Bergman, Ingrid * Odets, Bette * Simenon, Georges * VINCENT VAN GOGH (project) (Box 12, Folder 15)
  - APRIL 1954
    - J.R.'s contracts for FRENCH CANCAN - project "Van Gogh" with Van Heflin - J.R. to direct a stage version of JULES CESAR in Arles Amphitheatre. Includes correspondence regarding or with: * Heflin, Van * JULES CESAR * FRENCH CANCAN * VINCENT VAN GOGH (project) (Box 12, Folder 16)
  - MAY 1954
    - News of friends. Includes correspondence regarding or with: * Simenon, Georges (Box 12, Folder 17)
  - JUNE 1954
    - Birth of J.R.'s grandson Peter Renoir - news of friends - illness of Dudley Nichols - sale of the Martel Ave. house. Includes correspondence regarding or with: * Simenon, Georges * Nichols, Dudley (Box 12, Folder 18)
  - JULY 1954
    - J.R. beginning work on FRENCH CANCAN - preparations for ORVET - news of family and friends - J.R.'s salary to be paid for THE RIVER. Includes correspondence regarding or with: * Loew, David * McEldowney, Kenneth * Slade, Gabrielle * ORVET * FRENCH CANCAN * Nichols, Dudley * Caron, Leslie (Box 12, Folder 19)
  - AUGUST 1954
    - News of family and friends. Includes correspondence regarding or with: * Nichols, Dudley * Simenon, Georges * Slade, Gabrielle * FRENCH CANCAN (Box 12, Folder 20)
  - SEPTEMBER 1954
    - Photocopies of correspondence to and from Kenneth McEldowney re: (alleged) financial improprieties concerning THE RIVER - news of family and friends. Includes correspondence regarding or with: * McEldowney, Kenneth * RIVER, THE * Slade, Jean * Simenon, Georges * Slade, Gabrielle * Odets, Clifford * Nichols, Dudley (Box 12, Folder 21)
  - OCTOBER 1954
    - Preparations for ORVET, publicity for LE CARROSSE D'OR - news of family and friends. Includes correspondence regarding or with: * Slade, Gabrielle * Caron, Leslie * Hovald, Patrice * ORVET * CARROSSE D'OR, LE (Box 12, Folder 22)
  - NOVEMBER 1954
    - News of family. Includes correspondence regarding or with: * Slade, Jean * Slade, Gabrielle (Box 12, Folder 23)
  - DECEMBER 1954
    - Shooting of FRENCH CANCAN - preparations for ORVET - news of family and friends. Includes correspondence regarding or with: * Caron, Leslie * ORVET * Slade, Gabrielle * Smith, Bessie * FRENCH CANCAN (Box 12, Folder 24)
    - Offer of role in FRENCH CANCAN to Leslie Caron - news of family and friends. Includes correspondence regarding or with: * Caron, Leslie * Renoir, Alain * FRENCH CANCAN * Slade, Gabrielle (Box 15, Folder 22)
  - FEBRUARY 1955
    - Gallimard contract for publication rights to ORVET - news of friends. Includes correspondence regarding or with: * ORVET * Nichols, Dudley (Box 12, Folder 25)
  - MARCH 1955
    - Death of Louis Guillaume - rights to ORVET - news of family. Includes correspondence regarding or with: * Slade, Gabrielle * Nichols, Dudley * Guillaume, Louis (Box 12, Folder 26)
  - APRIL 1955
    - J.R.'s contract with C.I.M.U.R.A. - J.R.'s interest in producing Clifford Odets's play THE BIG KNIFE (LE GRANDE COUTEAU) - FRENCH CANCAN wins "Grand Prix de l'Academie du Cinema" for best French film of 1955 - news of friends - inludes photocopied correspondence. Includes correspondence regarding or with: * Ryan, Jessica * Nichols, Dudley * Loew, David * ORVET * Odets, Clifford * Auric, Georges * FRENCH CANCAN (Box 12, Folder 27)
  - MAY 1955
    - J.R. receives payment for author's share of ORVET German and Italian language adaptation rights - J.R.'s interest in producing Clifford Odets's play THE BIG KNIFE (LE GRAND COUTEAU) - news of family. Includes correspondence regarding or with: * Slade, Jean * Montel, Blanche * Odets, Clifford * GRAND COUTEAU, LE (Box 12, Folder 28)
  - JUNE 1955
    - Reactions to FRENCH CANCAN - publishing of J.R.'s song "Complainte de la Butte" from FRENCH CANCAN - J.R.'s interest in producing Clifford Odets's play THE BIG KNIFE (LE GRANDE COUTEAU) - news of family and friends. Includes correspondence regarding or with: * Odets, Clifford * GRAND COUTEAU, LE * Slade, Jean * Slade, Gabrielle * Nichols, Dudley * Kosma, Joseph * ORVET * FRENCH CANCAN (Box 12, Folder 29)
  - JULY 1955
    - J.R. receives payments for FRENCH CANCAN - preparations for JULES CESAR and ORVET - loan of artwork of Los Angeles County Museum of Art. Includes correspondence regarding or with: * Loew, David * Nichols, Dudley (Box 12, Folder 30)
  - AUGUST 1955
    - News of family and friends - publication of J.R.'s song "Complainte de la Butte" from FRENCH CANCAN - preparations for production of THE BIG KNIFE (LE GRANDE COUTEAU) - J.R.'s payments for ORVET. Includes correspondence regarding or with: * Nichols, Dudley * Montel, Blanche * ORVET * Serge, Jean * Slade, Gabrielle * Stravinsky, Igor (Box 12, Folder 31)
  - SEPTEMBER 1955
    - Rogers and Hammerstein's interest in adapting ORVET as a musical - news of family and friends. Includes correspondence regarding or with: * Spaak, Charles * ELENA ET LES HOMMES * ORVET * Slade, Gabrielle * Glass, Eric (Box 12, Folder 32)
  - OCTOBER 1955
    - ORVET synopsis sent to Rogers and Hammerstein - news of family and friends. Includes correspondence regarding or with: * Nichols, Dudley * Slade, Gabrielle * ORVET (Box 12, Folder 33)
  - NOVEMBER 1955
    - News of friends - loan of artwork to the Los Angeles County Museum of Art. Includes correspondence regarding or with: * Nichols, Dudley (Box 12, Folder 34)
  - DECEMBER 1955
    - Registration of "Complainte de la Butte" song from FRENCH CANCAN with Centre National de la Cinematographie. Includes correspondence regarding or with: * Watier, Lucienne * FRENCH CANCAN (Box 12, Folder 35)
  - JANUARY 1956
    - News of friends - business correspondence. Includes correspondence regarding or with: * Doynel, Ginette (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - FEBRUARY 1956
    - News of friends. Includes correspondence regarding or with: * Nichols, Dudley (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - MARCH 1956
    - Shooting ELENA ET LES HOMMES - preparations for production of THE BIG KNIFE (LE GRANDE COUTEAU) - news of friends - Italian rights to ORVET - includes photocopied correspondence. Includes correspondence regarding or with: * ORVET * GRAND COUTEAU, LE * Nichols, Dudley * Martel, Blanche * Odets, Clifford (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - APRIL 1956
    - Preparations for production of THE BIG KNIFE (LE GRANDE COUTEAU) - rights to ORVET - includes photocopied correspondence. Includes correspondence regarding or with: * Montel, Blanche * ORVET * Odets, Clifford * GRAND COUTEAU, LE (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - MAY-JUNE 1956
    - News of family - J.R. offers of his translation of Clifford Odets's LE GRANDE COUTEAU for publication. Includes correspondence regarding or with: * GRANDE ILLUSION, LA * Gallimard, Gaston * GRAND COUTEAU, LE * RIVER, THE (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - JULY 1956
    - Casting of THE BIG KNIFE (LE GRANDE COUTEAU) - news of family and friends - rights to ELENA ET LES HOMMES - J.R. working on RENOIR PAR RENOIR - English adaptation of ORVET. Includes correspondence regarding or with: * Slade, Gabrielle * Slade, Jean * Flaud, Jacques * Doynel, Ginette * GRAND COUTEAU, LE * ELENA ET LES HOMMES * Montel, Blanche * ORVET * Glass, Eric * Odets, Clifford * Braunberger, Pierre * Dewalde, Jean * Serge, Jean * RENOIR PAR RENOIR (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - AUGUST 1956
    - Casting of THE BIG KNIFE (LE GRANDE COUTEAU) - news of family - reactions to ELENA ET LES HOMMES - J.R. trying to acquire illegal copies of LA REGLE DU JEU. Includes correspondence regarding or with: * Bergman, Ingrid * ELENA ET LES HOMMES * REGLE DU JEU, LA * GRAND COUTEAU, LE * Caron, Leslie * O'Neill, Carlotta Monterrey * Slade, Gabrielle * Odets, Clifford (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - SEPTEMBER 1956
    - News of family and friends - J.R.'s lecture at Hunter College High School - recording of J.R.'s song "Complainte de la Butte" from FRENCH CANCAN - ELENA ET LES HOMMES: success in France and editing instructions. Includes correspondence regarding or with: * Blavette, Charles * Lichtig, Renee * Slade, Gabrielle * Deutschmeister, Henri * ELENA ET LES HOMMES * GRANDE ILLUSION, LA * ALBUM DE FAMILLE, L' * Montel, Blanche * Doynel, Ginette * Sicard, Suzanne * Sicard, Pierre * Serge, Jean * Simenon, Georges * Caron, Leslie * Meerson, Mary * Cocteau, Jean * Miller, Mitch * Meurisse, Paul * Ilyin, Maximilian (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - OCTOBER 1956
    - J.R.'s author's rights for L'ALBUM DE FAMILLE DE J.R. - news of friends - ELENA ET LES HOMME: dubbing in English and reactions to the film. Includes correspondence regarding or with: * ELENA ET LES HOMMES * Deutschmeister, Henri * Bazin, Andre * Doynel, Ginette * Montel, Blanche * Bergman, Ingrid * Kresel, Lee * Meurisse, Paul * Caron, Leslie * Clair, Rene * Cartier-Bresson, Henri * ALBUM DE FAMILLE, L' (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - NOVEMBER 1956
    - News of family and friends - English rights to ORVET - re-recording dialogue of ELENA ET LES HOMMES - J.R.'s rights to his old films. Includes correspondence regarding or with: * Nichols, Dudley * Von Stroheim, Erich * GRANDE ILLUSION, LA * Bergman, Ingrid * Lewin, Albert * Lestringuez, Marie * Meurisse, Paul * ORVET * Serge, Jean * Renoir, Claude, Jr. * Doynel, Ginette * Bazin, Andre (Box 13, Folder 10)
  - DECEMBER 1956
    - Earning statements for THE RIVER - plans to re-release LA GRANDE ILLUSION - J.R.'s salary not being paid for ELENA ET LES HOMMES. Includes correspondence regarding or with: * RIVER, THE * Doynel, Ginette * Brown, Kay * Renoir, Claude, Jr. * Kresel, Lee * Bergman, Ingrid * Blavette, Charles * ELENA ET LES HOMMES (Box 13, Folder 11)
    - Reactions to ELENA ET LES HOMMES - news of family and friends. Includes correspondence regarding or with: * Rossellini, Roberto * ELENA ET LES HOMMES * Koch, Carl * Vaughan, Olwen * Renoir, Alain * Reiniger, Lotte * Simenon, Georges (Box 15, Folder 23)
  - JANUARY 1957
    - Earning statements for THE RIVER and FRENCH CANCAN - news of family and friends - reactions to ELENA ET LES HOMMES in Rome - J.R.'s attempts to gain control of LA GRANDE ILLUSION distributuion - Ingrid Bergman's return to U.S.A. -J.R. not being paid for ELENA ET LES HOMMES - J.R.'s desire to have Erich Von Stroheim re-record dialogue for re-release of LA GRANDE ILLUSION. Includes correspondence regarding or with: * Renoir, Claude, Sr. * Renoir, Claude, Jr. * ELENA ET LES HOMMES * GRANDE ILLUSION, LA * Simenon, Georges * Tessier, Valentine * Serge, Jean * GRANDE ILLUSION, LA * Bergman, Ingrid * Doynel, Ginette * Von Stroheim, Erich * FRENCH CANCAN (Box 13, Folder 12)
  - FEBRUARY 1957
    - Earning statements for THE RIVER - plans for re-release of LA GRANDE ILLUSION - casting and plans for the stage production of THE BIG KNIFE (LE GRANDE COUTEAU) - projects with Leslie Caron - English translation of ORVET - ELENA ET LES HOMMES: reactions to the film and J.R.'s salary not being paid. Includes correspondence regarding or with: * Simenon, Georges * Serge, Jean * GRAND COUTEAU, LE * Caron, Leslie * Scott, Zachary * Meurisse, Paul * Bergman, Ingrid * Kresel, Lee * Doynel, Ginette * Griot, Jean * RIVER, THE * GRANDE ILLUSION, LA * Griffith, Richard * ORVET (Box 13, Folder 13)
  - MARCH 1957
    - Earning statements for THE RIVER - casting of THE BIG KNIFE (LE GRANDE COUTEAU) - news of friends - copies of LA GRANDE ILLUSION and TONI given to the Museum of Modern Art in New York - J.R. working on RENOIR PAR RENOIR - J.R.'s rights to his old films. Includes correspondence regarding or with: * Simenon, Georges * Serge, Jean * GRAND COUTEAU, LE * Scott, Zachary * Caron, Leslie * Meurisse, Paul * GRANDE ILLUSION, LA * Bergman, Ingrid * Kresel, Lee * Doynel, Ginette * Griot, Jean * RIVER, THE * Gaut, Pierre * RENOIR PAR RENOIR (Box 13, Folder 14)
  - APRIL 1957
    - Earning statements and contract copies for THE RIVER - preparations for THE BIG KNIFE (LE GRANDE COUTEAU) - project "Three Rooms in Manhattan" with Leslie Caron - illness of Erich Von Stroheim - J.R. working on RENOIR PAR RENOIR - J.R. attends the San Francisco film festival - bad editing by Warner Brothers of ELENA ET LES HOMMES and subsequent bad reviews. Includes correspondence regarding or with: * Renoir, Claude, Jr. * Serge, Jean * GRAND COUTEAU, LE * ELENA ET LES HOMMES * RIVER, THE * Serge, Jean * Simenon, Georges * Scott, Zachary * Eveillard-Vernac, Denise * Caron, Leslie * Meurisse, Paul * Bergman, Ingrid * RENOIR PAR RENOIR (Box 13, Folder 15)
  - MAY 1957
    - Sale of Renoir family home Les Collettes to France - news of family and friends - plans for re-release of LA GRANDE ILLUSION - project "Three Rooms in Manhattan" with Leslie Caron - invitations - death of Erich Von Stroheim. Includes correspondence regarding or with: * Renoir, Claude, Sr. * Renoir, Alain * Renoir, Claude, Jr. * Serge, Jean * GRAND COUTEAU, LE * Spaak, Charles * Simenon, Georges * Caron, Leslie * Bergman, Ingrid * Doynel, Ginette * Von Stroheim, Erich * Griffith, Richard * THREE ROOMS IN MANHATTAN (Box 13, Folder 16)
  - JUNE 1957